Guide to the Bassett Residence Hall records, 1950-1979 UA.31.16.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bassett Residence Hall records
1950-1979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Bassett Residence Hall
UA.31.16.0001
1.5 Linear Feet
Completed and occupied in the spring of 1927, Bassett Hall was first known as Dormitory No. 4. Bassett Residence Hall was home to female undergraduate students from the 1930s through the early 1990s. Types of material included in this collection are: correspondence, constitutions, financial summaries, minutes, notes, newsletters, clippings, a biography, rules, and scrapbooks. Major subjects include: Duke University, Trinity College, Bassett Hall, living groups, and female students. Materials date from 1950-1979.
1500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Bassett Residence Hall records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980.
Biographical/Historical note
Completed and occupied in the spring of 1927, Bassett Hall was first known as Dormitory No. 4. Like the other dormitories in the East Campus Georgian quadrangle, Dormitory No. 4 was designed to accommodate approximately 110 people and originally contained fifty single rooms, thirty double rooms, three parlors, a suite for the head of the house, kitchenette, pressing room, reception room, and offices. In 1930, it was renamed in honor of John Spencer Bassett, a professor of history at Trinity College (now Duke University).
Bassett Residence Hall was home to female undergraduate students from the 1930s through the early 1990s. The Omicron chapter of the Alpha Delta Pi sorority lived in Bassett Residence Hall from 1930-1935. Over the years, general direction for residential living groups came from Duke University, Trinity College and the Woman's College.
The women of Bassett Residence Hall also relied on the guidance and rules of the Women's Student Government Association, the Women's Residence Council, the Freshman Advisory Council, and the Baldwin Federation. The Baldwin Federation was established in 1974 to represent interests of undergraduate residents of Alspaugh, Basset, Brown, and Pegram Houses. As of 2006, Bassett Residence Hall remains co-ed and non-selective.
Scope and Contents note
Contains minutes of house meetings, financial summaries, house notebooks, a questionnaire, materials for new students, newsletters, general rules, and scrapbooks pertaining to the undergraduate female residents of Bassett Residence Hall at Duke University from 1950-1979.
Related Material
Arts and Sciences Council records
Duke University Archives
Association of Independent Houses records
Duke University Archives
Baldwin Federation records
Duke University Archives
Few Federation records
Duke University Archives
Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham; Women college students; Dormitories -- North Carolina; Residence and education; College freshmen -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Bassett Residence Hall; Duke University. Baldwin Federation; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. Woman’s College; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions
- Bassett Residence Hall governance and activities, 1950-1979, undated, 1950-1979, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence with new and returning students (also includes some photographs), house officer duties and lists, constitutions and some revisions, general house rules, minutes of monthly House Council meetings, notebooks kept by the house president, clippings, and a brief biography of John Spencer Bassett.
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Council officers, duties and lists, 1954-1970 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - Financial, 1972-1979 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1948-1979 (Box 1)
  - President's Notebooks, 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - General house rules, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Resident questionnaire, 1968 (Box 2)
  - The Houndstooth newsletter, circa 1969 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Week and Freshman Advisory Council, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Fliers and announcements, circa 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1950-1962 (Box 2)
  - Biography of John Spencer Bassett, undated (Box 2)
- Advisory and governance groups, 1954-1979
  Contains general correspondence, recommendations, and rules pertaining to the governance and organization of residence halls for women. The Baldwin Federation file pertains to residence hall governance and planning as part of a group of East Campus dormitories.
  - Baldwin Federation, circa 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Advisory Council, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Women's Student Government Association, circa 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Women's Residence Council, 1969 (Box 2)
  - General Woman's College, Trinity College, and Duke University rules for female residents, 1968-1979 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1962-1967
  Contains scrapbooks created by residents of Bassett Hall. The scrapbooks contain photographs, clippings, short writings, and some correspondence. Ordered by date.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 3, circa 1966-1967 (Box 3)